

Senior Full-Stack Software Engineer

Pedmonton, Alberta, Canada

✓ jd@jdlien.com

+1-780-702-3114

Portfolio Portfolio

GitHub

in LinkedIn

## SUMMARY

Senior software engineer with 10+ years of experience in backend and frontend development, specializing in PHP, Laravel, Vue, and React. Extensive background in systems administration, DevOps, and technical writing. Committed to developing high-quality, secure software with outstanding user experiences. Enthusiastic supporter of Apollo Scooters and the future of urban transportation.

### **EXPERIENCE**

### Freelance Developer / Technical Writer

Aug 2022 - Present

FullSpec Systems (Remote)

- Created system to rapidly ingest GTFS transit datasets from cities into MySQL & Postgres DBs.
- Built JSON:API-compatible API with Laravel to serve transit data to web and mobile apps.
- Designed public library registration system using Docker for quick deployment and upgrades.
- Created articles for PlanetScale such as <u>Upgrading MySQL to v8</u> and <u>Using SQL Joins</u>.
- Wrote technical articles for Readyset about implementing database caching in Laravel using AWS.
- Published <u>NPM Package</u> for frontend validation in TypeScript with 100% Vitest test coverage.

LANGUAGES PHP / Laravel / Livewire / TypeScript / React / JavaScript / TailwindCSS / Bash
TECHNOLOGIES MySQL / Postgres / Docker / AWS RDS / JSON:API / Git / nginx / Vitest / Jest

### Lead Web Developer

Nov 2019 – Apr 2024

**Edmonton Public Library** (Edmonton, Canada/Remote)

- Conceived and led a successful long-term project to migrate to Laravel and Vue.js from a legacy ColdFusion intranet with 60+ apps, enhancing robustness, user experience, and maintainability.
- Developed a system using database introspection to streamline CRUD interface creation across 50+ applications, reducing development time from weeks to hours for many apps, and centralizing code in a robust, well-tested library.
- Established formal development practices including local dev environments, staging servers, dev databases, and rigorous version control practices using GitHub, reducing mistakes on production.
- Led a major refactor of a ColdFusion codebase, modernizing and simplifying over 3,000 files into 800, enhancing code quality with reusable components and reduced complexity.
- Mentored 3 junior developers through curated training materials, hosting training sessions, and pairing, fostering collaboration and enhancing skills across the team.
- Dramatically improved security by implementing OAuth 2 and MFA, extensive automated testing, rewriting DB queries with strict parameter-binding, reducing incidents by 90%.

LANGUAGES PHP / Laravel / Vue.js / TypeScript / ColdFusion / Tailwind / PowerShell

TECHNOLOGIES MySQL / SQL Server / Azure / Git / Apache / IIS / Pest / PHPUnit / Jasmine

Edmonton Public Library (Edmonton, Canada)

- Won Innovation Award for development and successful launch of Makerspace Booking System by working closely with staff. Reduced customer booking complaints and cut staff booking time by 70%.
- Initiated and developed an error management system to log user-reported issues, collect detailed feedback, and notify developers, enabling proactive resolution and improved system reliability.
- Developed online registration system to automate customer account creation for 50,000+ customers, reducing staff time spent on manual account creation, while mitigating fraudulent account activity.
- Built CMS, form builder, APIs, and >30 other apps in response to organizational needs for about 900 staff using responsive design and accessible design.
- Demonstrated exceptional responsiveness by addressing issue reports and enhancement requests, often delivering solutions or upgrades within an hour on the same day.
- Optimized SQL Server database design and tuned queries, increasing database performance for slow queries up to 10x.

LANGUAGES PHP / ColdFusion / ColdBox / jQuery / JavaScript / CSS / Sass / PowerShell

TECHNOLOGIES MySQL / SQL Server / Git / Apache / IIS / TestBox

## Freelance Developer / Systems Administrator

Sep 2011 - Apr 2012

FullSpec Systems (Edmonton, Canada/Remote)

- Developed web applications for small businesses.
- Created and administered WordPress and Drupal sites.
- Managed network infrastructure, DNS, and email systems.
- Administered Linux and Windows servers and workstations.

## **Technical Copywriter**

Jan 2010 - Sep 2011

Opera Software (Oslo, Norway)

- Wrote content for Opera blogs about web standards and browsers.
- Collaborated with developers and product team to write documentation.
- Planned and wrote marketing copy for 18 product launches and major updates.
- Won international blogging competition, with posts selected from over 300 submissions.

#### **EDUCATION**

# **Computing & Information Systems**

2015 - 2021

**Athabasca University** 

Graduated with distinction. Academic focus on web development and business.

# **Business Analyst Certificate**

2007 - 2008

Northern Alberta Institute of Technology

Developed requirements gathering, project documentation, and quality assurance skills.

# **Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA)**

2007

Certified in networking fundamentals, routing, switching, and Cisco IOS administration.

# **PROJECTS**

### Validator NPM Package

To improve the UX of forms, I created an NPM package, <u>@jdlien/validator on Github</u>, that makes it easy to add powerful frontend validation to forms. This lets users do things like type anything resembling a date and have it magically reformatted the way the developer wants. It has no dependencies, is thoroughly tested (100% code coverage with Vitest), is well-documented, and is easy to use for developers and users alike.

### WebArtisan.info Tech Blog

A technical blog I run has articles about PHP, Tailwind, JavaScript, CSS and software careers. It won an award in a Hashnode Blogging Competition. Notable articles include:

- The Pros and Cons of Tailwind CSS
- What is Dependency Injection?
- How I Made My '80s Retro-Style HomePage

### Writing for <a href="mailto:php[architect">php[architect</a>] Magazine

I occasionally write for a magazine focused on PHP. My article about using attributes in PHP 8+ was published in the June 2024 issue.

# MEGA World (Multiplayer Educational Game)

A Laravel & Livewire-based video game with a complex MySQL database for academic research into learning via gamification in collaboration with Athabasca University. I also created all the graphics assets in WebP and SVG using Photoshop and Illustrator.

# FunctionalColor Keyboard Plugin

For mechanical keyboards using Kaleidoscope firmware, I created <u>a plugin to change the color of keys</u> based on type of key on the active layer. Done in C++ for Arduino using lots of tricky compiler operation to achieve extreme memory efficiency.